Guide to the Dept. of Institution Management records, 1927-1968.
Dept. of Institution Management records, 1927-1968
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Dept. of Institution Management records, 1927-1968.
23-15-776
New York State College of Home Economics. Dept. of Institution Management.
2 Cubic Feet.
Correspondence, photographs, reports, papers, blueprints.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, minutes, reports, photographs, blueprints, and other material pertaining to the Cafeteria Management (later Institution Management) departments, and other matters pertaining to industrial nutrition and education. Includes papers of Kathleen Cutlar, Alice Burgoin and Katherine W. Harris.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
In 1969 the Department of Institution Management and the Department of Food and Nutrition merged to become the Department of Human Nutrition and Food.
In 1974 the Board of Trustees voted to abolish the Department of Human Nutrition and Food in the College of Human Ecology and the Graduate School of Nutrition to establish the Division of Nutritional Sciences, an intercollege unit within the Colleges of Agriculture and Life Sciences and Human Ecology.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, minutes, reports, photographs, blueprints, and other material pertaining to the Cafeteria Management (later Institution Management) departments, including the papers of a professor of Institutional Management, Kathleen Cutlar. Subjects include the Purnell Project, "Training Schools," classroom activities, planning of Martha Van Rensselaer Hall, and other matters pertaining to industrial nutrition and education. Includes papers of Alice Burgoin and Katherine W. Harris.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State College of Home Economics.; Burgoin, Alice, 1902-1971.; Cutlar, Kathleen.; Harris, Katherine W.; Cornell University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Associations, institutions, etc.--Management--Study and teaching.; Cafeterias.; Cookery.; Food industry and trade.; Food service--Study and teaching.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Memos and Correspondence
Series II. Department Programs and Research
Series III. Blueprints, Photographs and Specifications of MVR Hall
Series IV. Recipes, Food Selection and Preparation
Series V. Department Programs and Specialities
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Memos and Correspondence
  - Department Memos and Reports, 1939-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Department Memos and Reports, 1939-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Department Goals and Annual Report, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1955-02-1955-03 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1929-09-16-1961-11-17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1963-03-06-1963-05-15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1962-02-09-1963-02-27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1963-06-03-1963-08-09 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1963-08-09-1963-12-12 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1964-02-24-1964-07-31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1964-09-09-1965-02-16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1965-03-01-1965-05-12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1965-05-19-1966-01-03 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Memos and Correspondence, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence Concerning Graduate Student Quotas, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 16A)
  - American Food Service Association - Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, Memos, Radio Scripts, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II. Department Programs and Research
  - Articles - "I.M. Course at C.U. Gives Students Training for Chosen Life Work" and "The Course in Hotel Administration", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "A Half Century of Achievement" and Plans for Kitchen in Comstock Hall, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Papers - Division of Industrial Relations, Women in Industry and Minimum Wage, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Migrant Farm Labor Program, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Articles and Reports by Katherine Harris, 1934-1951 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mixer Film - Plans and Script, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Report on a Year of Study at Cornell, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Research Articles, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Training School Program for Teachers of Mass Feeding Courses - Schedule, Menu, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Training School for Industrial Nutritionists - Schedules, 1944-11 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - School Lunch Training School, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - New York State Emergency Food Commission, 1945-06 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Institution Management 101, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - History of Institution Management, 1945-06 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Articles re: Institution Management, 1947-1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Articles re; Institution Management, 1947-1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Course Outlines - Institution Management, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Student Personnel Handbook - Home Economics Cafeteria, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Fall
  - Master's Degrees Conferred in the Department- list, 1937-1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Publications List for the Department, 1939-1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Series III. Blueprints, Photographs and Specifications of MVR Hall
  - Green Room Luncheon, 1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Photos of MVR Hall, Tea Room, Cafeteria, Kitchen (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cafeteria - Articles, Staff Meeting Minutes, 1936-1961 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Cafeteria Equipment and Specifications (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Specifications - Kitchen and Cafeteria Equipment and Refrigerators (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Blueprints - Dishwashing and Service Plan, Bakery (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Blueprints - Kitchen Plan, Stainless Steel Shelf (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Blueprints - Steamer, Range, Counters, Scullery (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Blueprints - Service Room (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Blueprints - Equipment for the Home Economics Building (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Blueprints - Counter (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Series IV. Recipes, Food Selection and Preparation
  - Recipes - Use of Non-Fat Dry Milk, Eggplant, Cakes, Cookies, and Frosting, 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Recipes - Vegetable, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Recipes - Bread - Directions for Cooking Vegetables and Sandwiches (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Recipes - Desserts, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Party Refreshments, Low Cost Menus, Recipes - Meat, Liver, Poultry, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Recipes - Fish, Meat, Extended Meatless, List of Cafeteria Foods, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Meat Substitutes, Cake Recipes, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Recipes - Fish, Dressing, Relishes, Vegetables, 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Salad Dressings, Hot Breads, Pies, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Desserts and Dessert Sauces (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Salads (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sandwiches, Salad Dressings, Dressings, Relishes, and Sauces, 1939-1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Quantity Food Preparation - Aims, Organization, Guiding Laws, Precautions, Marketing Aids, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Quantity Food Preparation - Meat Charts, Proportions, Price List, List of Foods, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Quantity Food Preparation - Work Sheets, Office, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Quantity Food Preparation - Menu Planning, Green Room - Job Analysis, 1934-1937 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Emergency and Wartime Food Articles, 1943-1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - German Army Soya Cookbook, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Wartime Meat Recipes (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Pamphlets - Preserving Fruits and Vegetables, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Food Selection Guidelines (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series V. Department Programs and Specialities
  - School, Hospital, and Institution Kitchens, 1943-1959 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Community Kitchens (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Camp Meals (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Mobile Kitchens, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Photographs of Mobile Kitchen, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Plans and Blueprints of Mobile Kitchen, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Negatives of Mobile Kitchen, 1942 (Box 2)